Okay, בוקר טוב. boker tov. Today's דף daf is כ"א, chaf-aleph, 21.
We are,
it's a short דף daf and we're a little ahead. Part of
the reason it's a short דף daf is you see this huge
תוספות Tosafot on כ"א עמוד ב', chaf-aleph amud bet, חלב, halav, which
is basically trying to figure out how do we generally rule whether
generally we're concerned for minority possibilities. Oops, hold on, I forgot to
swipe this.
Okay, we'll keep on going. Anyway, so the huge תוספות Tosafot was
because that we did yes, that made the דף daf short yesterday
was because the question is whether, you know, if you remember yesterday
the whole issue is are we, what's going on here? Anyway, whatever.
Anyway, the whole issue is are we concerned with minority possibilities and
what if there's a חזקה chazakah to support it and what if
it's לחומרא l'chumra or לקולא? l'kula? Anyway, תוספות Tosafot tries to figure
out how we rule. So that made yesterday's דף daf short and
today's דף daf is actually very short just because the גמרא Gemara
is not so, not so conceptually complicated but just, you know, the
actual details of the case described are a little bit challenging so
we have a very large רש"י Rashi and תוספות. Tosafot. But let's
take a look. So the issue we've been dealing with has been,
you know, the question about when sheep or a goat gives birth,
whether you assume it's the first birth or not for בכור bechor
if you don't know the history of the animal and whether you
have to be concerned about a prior miscarriage. So the גמרא Gemara
yesterday had given a scenario, a ברייתא baraita that had given a
scenario about a case where you could take מעשר בהמה ma'aser behemah
from the births of all of one sheep. Now not that a
sheep could give birth or goat rather to give birth ten kids.
מעשר בהמה ma'aser behemah is only the animals that are born from
ראש חודש אלול Rosh Chodesh Elul until the next ראש חודש אלול.
Rosh Chodesh Elul. ראש חודש אלול Rosh Chodesh Elul is ראש השנה
למעשר בהמה. Rosh Hashanah l'ma'aser behemah. And
but it would be a case where the goat gave birth to
three kids and each of the kids gave birth, I don't know
what is this, and each of the kids gave birth to three
more kids and since the gestation period for the goats is five
months, so that can happen and you can have three kids and
nine grandkids and twelve new children in a year and take מעשר
בהמה. ma'aser behemah. So all of that was fine. What was the
point of that? So the גמרא Gemara said that the issue was
that first issue was was we had said yesterday that it might
not be possible for an animal to give birth again in the
same year that it miscarried. And here the question was why don't
we say the mother who first had three kids then had a
second set of kids? Why do we only speak about the kids
having grandkids and doesn't this prove that an animal once it has
miscarried cannot give birth? And the גמרא Gemara said look, it's possible
after a miscarriage you can give birth in the same year. But
this was a case where the mother first had live children, had
three kids, and therefore we have to speak about the children having
children, not about her having another set of children because to give
two births, separate births in the same year, that maybe is not
possible. With that in mind, we go further. So let's take a
look now, four lines from the top of כ"א עמוד א'. chaf-aleph
amud aleph. The גמרא Gemara says the following. אמר רבי שמעון אני
ראיתי גדיה. Amar Rabbi Shimon, ani ra'iti gedi'ah. Rabbi Shimon said, I
saw a goat give birth and having מעשר בהמה ma'aser behemah all
within the same year, which seems to just be a paraphrase of
what the תנא קמא Tanna Kamma says. So the גמרא Gemara is
going to try to figure out what's their, what are they debating?
And it's going to sound like a real repeat of what we
said yesterday. So the גמרא Gemara says, מאי איכא בין תנא קמא
לרבי שמעון? mai ika bein Tanna Kamma l'Rabbi Shimon? What's the difference?
תנא קמא Tanna Kamma gave a scenario, three kids, nine grandkids, מעשר
בהמה ma'aser behemah in one year. And Rabbi Shimon said I saw
a case of מעשר בהמה ma'aser behemah in one year. What's the
difference? That could be. Okay, anyway, so the גמרא Gemara says, איכא
בינייהו דזעירי. ika beinaihu d'Ze'iri. The issue about Ze'iri, about if you
remember Ze'iri was a question about after a miscarriage, can an animal,
how long does an animal have to wait before becoming pregnant again?
30 days. תנא קמא איתא דזעירי רבי שמעון ליתא דזעירי. Tanna Kamma
itai d'Ze'iri, Rabbi Shimon leitai d'Ze'iri. The תנא קמא Tanna Kamma holds
of it, Rabbi Shimon does not. Now what the heck does Ze'iri
have to do with our discussion? Like Ze'iri is after a miscarriage,
we're not talking about a miscarriage. So we're not talking about the
mother getting pregnant again or not. I mean, what is this relevant?
So that's why you have a huge רש"י Rashi and huge תוספות.
Tosafot. Okay, because it does not exactly clear what is going on
here. Now the best explanation which רש"י Rashi doesn't like for technical
reasons but it fits in the best is the following: that what
Rabbi Shimon is saying is that we are actually are counting the
mother, as opposed to what we assumed
yesterday, we are actually saying the mother is going to count toward
the מעשר בהמה. ma'aser behemah. The mother itself was born in the
same year as the kids and the grandkids. Okay, you with me
so? The basic, now we've got a case where the mother is
born, she has one set of kids, those kids have more kids.
Okay, now the point is like this. So if the mother is
born,
so three generations are counted? What? So the three generations are counted?
Three generations, right, right, they're all new sheep and therefore you take
מעשר בהמה ma'aser behemah at the same time. Now the mother is
born, so the mother gets pregnant, let's say she's born on ראש
חודש אלול, Rosh Chodesh Elul, okay, because that's when the year starts.
The mother is born on ראש חודש אלול. Rosh Chodesh Elul. Now
she's going to get pregnant and have kids. For some reason we're
going to assume
that she won't get pregnant the first month that she's born. Okay,
we haven't said that so far but let's assume that. Okay. So
she gets pregnant, that's teenage pregnancy. So she'll get pregnant, she'll get
pregnant once she's a month old, okay, ראש חודש תשרי, Rosh Chodesh
Tishrei, alright? She gets pregnant then. Five months pregnancy. So, תשרי, Tishrei,
חשוון, Cheshvan, כסלו, Kislev, טבת, Tevet, שבט, Shevat, she gives birth on
ראש חודש אדר. Rosh Chodesh Adar. Everybody with me? Okay, she gives
birth on ראש חודש אדר Rosh Chodesh Adar to her three kids.
Those kids now also wait a month.
Now those kids right now, those kids also presumably can't also get,
you know, give birth the first month that they are born, okay,
get pregnant. So they wait until ראש חודש ניסן, Rosh Chodesh Nissan,
okay, and then they have five months. So, ניסן, Nissan, אייר, Iyar,
סיוון, Sivan, תמוז, Tammuz, אב, Av, okay, and now the problem is
if that gave birth on ראש חודש אלול, Rosh Chodesh Elul, that's
already into the next year. So we've got a little bit of
a problem, right? Are you going into, right, are you going into
the next year or not? So that's the issue here. Now, how
is that relating to זעירי? Zeiri? It's relating... before you have a
question, let's explain this point. It's hard enough as it is. So
hold on,
let me just check רש"י Rashi one more second. Hold on, make
sure I'm saying this right.
Right, so the issue, one minute, hold on.
Yeah, so that's part of...
one minute, one minute.
Okay, so anyway, so רש"י, Rashi, that's part of what bothers רש"י,
Rashi, of course, is what bothers רש"י Rashi is that how are,
if you're being that exact, how is it, oops, how is it
that this second, thank you, how is it that this second crop
is born before ראש חודש אלול? Rosh Chodesh Elul? It should be
that they're born on ראש חודש אלול. Rosh Chodesh Elul. So maybe
the question is, right, so part of the answer is is that
we're not saying that it has to be that we're sort of
fudging it a little. I mean while we set this up that
it worked out like exact, in principle really an animal could get
pregnant within its first month. So the second crop of animals actually
did not have to wait a month to get pregnant, they got
pregnant within the first month. Right there sometime when we say in
אייר... Iyar... no, in אדר, Adar, I'm sorry, they got pregnant in
אדר. Adar. Anyway, it was possible to get pregnant within the first
month. So therefore that's how we set up the scenario. If the
first animal waited until it was one month old, but in general
that's not required. So wait, so we're constructing this whole case, okay,
got it? Born, waited a month, had its three kids. Those three
kids got pregnant right away, had more kids, and then you have
the whole family of ten animals, actually thirteen animals, that have מעשר
בהמה. Ma'aser Behemah. So then what is the big deal about all
this? The only question then becomes whether this mother, the one who
was born at ראש חודש אדר, Rosh Chodesh Adar, can have another
kid in this period of time. That's the only question. Okay. And
the issue is is that if we hold like זעירי, Zeiri, and
זעירי Zeiri says that after a miscarriage you can't have, what?
Have another kid after the grandchildren.
After after the children. She had her children on ראש חודש אדר,
Rosh Chodesh Adar, okay? And now can she get pregnant again and
have another kid within the remaining six months? And the answer is
is that, well, if she can get pregnant within the first month
after birth, then yes. But if she can only get pregnant after
the first month after birth, which is what זעירי Zeiri says, he's
talking about miscarriages, this would be birth, but if she can only
get pregnant after the first month after birth, then she cannot have
kids within the next six months, it would have to be six
months plus. Okay, so that is how רש"י Rashi is explaining the
case, that the whole question, the whole, thank you, I heard that,
the whole question is I don't want those kids,
I know, well, that's why there's other explanations. If you want, we
could do the other explanations in רש"י, Rashi, but for now the
only thing that bothers רש"י Rashi here is that why are we
sort of treating the mother different than the kids? Anyway, fine. But
let's just work with this. The whole question according to רש"י Rashi
is that the mother was born, had birth after, you know, got
pregnant after one month, had kids, and can that happen again and
all within the same year? And that's hinging on זעירי, Zeiri, whether
it has to wait a month after birth. Let me just, I'll
take your questions, but while keeping this scenario in mind, and I
will give you an alternate scenario if you really want to hear
it, let's just finish the other possibilities in the גמרא, Gemara, which
is exactly what we said yesterday, which all plays off on this
question of, you know, of do you have to wait a month,
can you have kids in the next six months after her birth?
So the first issue is whether she had to wait a month,
which was זעירי. Zeiri. רבי שמעון בן לקיש דזעירי. Rebbe Shimon ben
Lakish d'Zeiri. איבעית אימא Iba'it eima if you want you could say
דכולי עלמא אית להו דזעירי, dekulu alma ithu d'Zeiri, everybody holds like
זעירי, Zeiri, had to wait a month, so how is it possible
to have another set of kids within the next six months? הכא
ביולדת למקוטעין קמיפלגי, Hecha b'yoledet limkuta'in kamiflegi,
whether an animal has to have five full months of pregnancy and
give birth in less than five full months. Basically going back to
what we said yesterday. תנא קמא Tanna kamma אין יולדת למקוטעין, ein
yoledet limkuta'in, according to the opinion that she could not had kids
within that same year a second time, then it would need five
full months, so the next she could have had kids would have
been ראש חודש אדר. Rosh Chodesh Adar. אלול, Elul, excuse me. רבי
שמעון יולדת, Rabbi Shimon yoledet, and רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon says she
could have kids within it, it doesn't require five full months of
pregnancy, so she could have more kids even before ראש חודש אלול.
Rosh Chodesh Elul. ואי בעית אימא, Ve'ee ba'isayma, if you want you
could say, דכולי עלמא אינה יולדת למקוטעין, dechulei alma einah yoledet limikutain,
everybody would agree that you can't have less than five full months.
The question is, what does full mean? והכא במקצת היום ככולו קמיפלגי,
Vehacha bemiktzat hayom kekulo kamiflagi,
whether that very last day of the fifth month, do you need
that full last day of the fifth month? If you do need
the full last day, then you cannot, then she can't have her
kids till ראש חודש אלול. Rosh Chodesh Elul. If you don't need
the full last day, she can have her kids on the last
day of what? אב. Av. On the last day of אב. Av.
והכא במקצת היום ככולו קמיפלגי. Vehacha bemiktzat hayom kekulo kamiflagi. The תנא
קמא Tana Kama לא אמרינן מקצת היום ככולו, lo amrinan miktzat hayom
kekulo, he does not say the last day of אב Av counts
as the full last day of the month, so she would only
be able to give birth on ראש חודש אלול, Rosh Chodesh Elul,
pretty funny applying a halachic category to a biological reality. רבי שמעון
אמרינן מקצת היום ככולו, Rabbi Shimon amrinan miktzat hayom kekulo, רבי שמעון
Rabbi Shimon says you do say מקצת היום ככולו, miktzat hayom kekulo,
and therefore she could have given birth. ואי בעית אימא, Ve'ee ba'isayma,
if you want you could say, דכולי עלמא אמרינן מקצת היום ככולו,
dechulei alma amrinan miktzat hayom kekulo, everybody agrees she could have given
birth on that last day. Ah, so she could have given birth
on that last day, so why does the תנא קמא Tana Kama
say that the mother describes a scenario that the mother did not
give birth a second time? והכא במחוסר זמן נכנס לדיר להתעשר קמיפלגי.
Vehacha bemechusar zman nichnas ledirei aser kamiflagi.
Yes, maybe the mother did give birth on the last day of
אב, Av, but nevertheless he says that that second child cannot be
part of מעשר. ma'aser. Why? Because the question is, can you take
מעשר בהמה ma'aser behemah on an animal before it's eight days old?
You can't bring a קרבן korban less than eight days old. Can
you take מעשר בהמה ma'aser behemah on an animal less than eight
days old? So yes, it's possible it was given birth, it was
one day old on the last day of the animal year, on
the last day of אב, Av, but is it still part of
the group for מעשר בהמה ma'aser behemah if it's only one day
old? And then the גמרא, Gemara, right, says, now we're into a
different conversation, a halachic conversation which we can get into, and that's
what we'll get to as we turn the page, whether you can
take מעשר בהמה ma'aser behemah less than one, less than eight days
old. Now we can have our questions on this scenario.
My question is, this is a basic question, I mean, animals don't
give birth at certain times, you can't just move this whole thing
around, or like, you know, we're like assuming that, you know, whatever
it is, that day they... That's right.
That is a very good question too. I don't know.
They probably knew that then.
Yeah, I mean, that's also part of the reason by the way
why ראש חודש אלול, Rosh Chodesh Elul, because that's normally the time
after, you know, there's a period when they go into heat and
the period when they copulate and the period when they give birth,
and this sort of marks the line between last year and this
year. Yeah, that's a very good point. I don't know. I mean,
so much of this conversation is purely theoretical. You know, as I
know Bobby was objecting to, to the issue of after one month.
Do you know how long, when animals can start to copulate? No
idea.
Just the thought of a one-month-old anything getting pregnant is so
outrageous, it doesn't even...
But animals mature so much faster than humans. Oh my god. Not
that fast.
All right. Usually it's after the first year. Well, first year. Yeah,
but that's...
Right, well, that's what
the גמרא Gemara was talking about.
That's what the גמרא Gemara was talking about yesterday. Yeah, so...
But maybe because this is already... Just in the last couple of
days, if the גמרא Gemara is being so specific about מקצת היום
ככולו miktzat hayom kekulo and one day, I mean, you could investigate
from a calendar point of view, what if there were, you know,
two מלאים malei's in...
So תוספות Tosafot asks that question.
...what do you call it, שנה מעוברת. shanah me'uberet.
Right, right. Oh, so actually the שנה מעוברת... shanah me'uberet... So תוספות
Tosafot first of all asks that question about... This sort of reminds
me of the joke. You know the joke, the guy goes to
the rabbi, tells him how do I build my סוכה? sukkah? He
says, well, גמרא דף י"ג Gemara Daf Yud Gimmel and this רש"י,
Rashi, and he goes out and he builds the whole סוכה, sukkah,
and then, you know, and based on the גמרא Gemara and the
רש"י, Rashi, and as he's nailing the last nail, the whole thing
collapses. So he comes to the rabbi, he says, I did exactly
what you said, but the סוכה sukkah collapsed. Ah, that's תוספות's Tosafot
question.
So anyway, so apparently yes, that's תוספות's Tosafot question here. He says,
how does רש"י Rashi say five months and make it exactly work
according to the calendar? What about the חסר chaser and the מעוברת?
me'uberet? That's one set of questions תוספות Tosafot has, he doesn't really
directly answer that. The other issue about the מעוברת me'uberet calendar is
interesting, and I think in one place, right, רש"י Rashi tries to
say, again, in a different way רש"י Rashi describes the scenario here,
that that was the difference between the תנא קמא Tana Kama and
רבי שמעון. Rabbi Shimon. That when רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon said בתוך
שנתה, betoch shenatah, it meant literally a year, like of a year
of time, and when the תנא קמא Tana Kama said... what did
he say? Right, right, it could be within a year of time,
and when the תנא קמא Tana Kama says that it's that you
can get it from אלול Elul to אלול, Elul, that was incorporating
the possibility of a שנה מעוברת. shanah me'uberet. So again, it's not
exactly clear where it is in the גמרא, Gemara, but רש"י Rashi
wants to say maybe that's part of the difference. You know, how
does the גמרא Gemara mean, how does the גמרא Gemara know, if
you, the גמרא Gemara we just read, רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon basically
is saying that it's easier to get... oh, maybe he says of
רבי יוחנן.
Rabbi Yochanan. How does the גמרא Gemara say it?
That according to...
Oh, now I don't even know. Anyway, the way we just read
it, the תנא קמא Tanna Kamma is saying that you're not going
to get something included in the מעשר בהמה Ma'aser Behemah where רבי
שמעון Rebbi Shimon says you will. If you want, if you want
I could take a look here what רש״י Rashi speaks about the,
about the ראש חודש, Rosh Chodesh, hold on, about the מעוברת. me'uberet.
Let me see if I can just quickly find it. Maybe it
was תוספות, Tosafot, hold on. Yeah, רש״י, Rashi, hold on one minute.
תנא קמא דלא נקט לשון דתוך איתי דאירי ותו גם מקבל
זכר דראש חודש מיניה ולא מקדש שלמים עד יום
אחד בשנה שניה.
Tanna Kamma d'lo nakat lishon d'toch itei d'iri
v'tu gam m'kabel
zakhar d'Rosh Chodesh minei v'lo m'kadesh shlamim ad yom
echad b'shanah shniyah.
Okay, right, right, right. So רש״י Rashi basically, here's one way רש״י
Rashi explains the scenario. רש״י Rashi says both רבי שמעון Rebbi Shimon
and the תנא קמא Tanna Kamma agree that the mother gave birth
a second time and that that's the scenario, or that
the kids gave birth, whatever it is, that it was able to
happen. But what the תנא קמא Tanna Kamma says is that it
does מעשר
בהמה, Ma'aser Behemah, meaning מעשר בהמה Ma'aser Behemah all means it have
to happen before ראש חודש אלול. Rosh Chodesh Elul. So the תנא
קמא, Tanna Kamma, in order for it to happen a second time,
whatever the it was, right, but in order for it to happen
a second time, all you needed was that it happened before ראש
חודש אלול. Rosh Chodesh Elul. Fine, it could be a leap year.
For רבי שמעון Rebbi Shimon goes further, and רבי שמעון Rebbi Shimon
says, no, I heard it happened בתוך שנתו, b'toch shnato, which means
literally within twelve months. So according to him, how could that scenario
happen within twelve months if you know, without the idea of leap
year? So that's why the גמרא Gemara has to say there are
ways he can stretch the time, right? There's ways he can get
more to take place. Either he doesn't hold of עירי, 'iri, so
it can get pregnant within the month, or that it doesn't need
five full months. But anyway, רש״י Rashi tries to read the מעוברת
me'uberet question into what's in one version of רש״י Rashi into what's
going on. That the תנא קמא Tanna Kamma is just saying it
happened, all it has to do is happen before ראש חודש אלול,
Rosh Chodesh Elul, whereas רבי שמעון Rebbi Shimon is saying, no, no,
no, it can even happen within twelve months, and therefore he has
to have a more, you know, flexible way of saying how it
could happen in order to make it happen within twelve months.
Yeah, so just the ones that came up with the first Google
searches were pigs, dogs, and cats, which is four months.
Four months, okay. So anyway, four months.
All right, four is the earliest, six is what's in the משנה.
Mishnah.
Okay, if it makes it easier, the other way רש״י Rashi says,
so given your objections, very reasonable objections, that this animal is getting
pregnant one month after it's born, I will tell you the other
read of רש״י Rashi that רש״י Rashi actually prefers, but it's just
harder because the question is what forced the גמרא Gemara to create
this scenario. But the read that רש״י Rashi preferred is, no, no,
the mother sheep has been, who knows how old she is, her
goat, she's a year old, that's not a problem. She just gave
birth to three kids. Oh no, it's still a problem because those
kids have to give birth. Yeah, that's still not going to solve
it because that
thing, that generation is going to have to give birth.
Yeah, so it's not going to work. All right, let's move on.
They definitely knew that.
Yeah, I don't know. Let's move on, okay? There's a reason why
there is a huge רש״י תוספות Rashi Tosafot here. Normally, normally you
only have these huge רש״י Rashi תוספות Tosafot if there's like other
סוגיות sugyot that have to be reconciled or something is very conceptually
problematic. So every now and then you get it because it's just
like the scenario the גמרא Gemara is talking about doesn't seem to
make sense and you just have to try to reconstruct the scenario.
So רש״י Rashi basically has like three versions about it. I gave
you one. Let's move on. Okay, so putting that behind us and
moving on, we now have established, we've established that one possible issue
is whether an animal is just born before ראש חודש אלול Rosh
Chodesh Elul and it's not yet eight days old, can it be
part of מעשר בהמה? Ma'aser Behemah? Okay, so let's take a look.
והתניא, V'ha tanya, what, והתניא V'ha tanya we'll see how the גמרא
Gemara frames it. רבי שמעון בן יהודה אומר משום רבי שמעון, Rebbi
Shimon ben Yehudah omer mishum Rebbi Shimon, רבי שמעון בן יהודה Rebbi
Shimon ben Yehudah says in the name of רבי
שמעון, Rebbi Shimon, and סתם רבי שמעון, stam Rebbi Shimon, does anybody
know? Is רבי שמעון בר יוחאי. Rebbi Shimon bar Yochai. Okay, normally
we only hear רבי שמעון בר יוחאי Rebbi Shimon bar Yochai when
talking about the זוהר, Zohar, but actually סתם רבי שמעון stam Rebbi
Shimon in the גמרא Gemara is רבי שמעון בר יוחאי. Rebbi Shimon
bar Yochai. Anyway, so רבי שמעון בן יהודה Rebbi Shimon ben Yehudah
says in the name of רבי שמעון, Rebbi Shimon, מחוסר זמן נכנס
לדיר להתעשר, mechusar zman nichnas l'dir l'hit'aser, that even an animal that,
so here it is exactly the same רבי שמעון Rebbi Shimon position,
the animal could be not yet eight days old and still be
מעשר, Ma'aser, והרי הן כבכור, v'harei hen k'bechor, just like a בכור
bechor of an animal, מה בכור קדוש לפני זמנו, mah bechor kadosh
lifnei zmano, the same way a בכור bechor the minute it's born,
even though it's not eight days old, געזונטהייט, gezuntheit, and can't be
brought as a קרבן korban is קדוש, kadosh, וקרב לאחר זמנו, v'karev
l'achar zmano, but you only bring it as a קרבן korban once
it's eight days old, אף מחוסר זמן, af mechusar zman, even an
animal not yet eight days old, קדוש לפני זמנו, kadosh lifnei zmano,
can be an animal but for מעשר Ma'aser can be sanctified before
the time, וקרב לאחר זמנו, v'karev l'achar zmano, and is brought after
its time. Now, everybody admits that this is not the case by
normal קרבנות. korbanot. By normal קרבנות, korbanot, the גמרא, Gemara, I mean
the תורה Torah says, מיום השמיני והלאה ירצה להקריב קרבן לה׳, miyom
hashmini v'halah yeiratzeh l'hakriv korban l'Hashem, it's only from eight days old
will it be desirable to be a קרבן, korban, and חז״ל Chazal
understand that that means that even if you try to sanctify it
less than eight days old, it's not sanctified. So here he's saying,
ah, but the exception to that rule is בכור, bechor, because בכור
bechor is קדוש kadosh the moment it's born, right, that's
clear. whether מעשר maaser, *ma'aser* is even animals less than eight days
old on ראש חודש אלול *Rosh Chodesh Elul*. So now we go
on. So the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says like this: Actually, there is
an interesting alternative, which is you could say if it's less—I haven't
checked this out—but if it's less than eight days old on ראש
חודש אלול *Rosh Chodesh Elul*, maybe it's still part of the previous
year for מעשר maaser בהמה *ma'aser behemah*, I just have to wait
a few days before doing the process, take מעשר maaser *ma'aser*, right?
There's one question which is which year is it part of for
my taking of the מעשר maaser *ma'aser*, and the other is the
act of sanctifying it and of taking of the מעשר maaser *ma'aser*,
that it can't be eight days old for. So logically you would
think, and this might be true, I have to check it, that
they might say you can't take מעשר Maaser *ma'aser* when it's less
than eight days old. You wait a few days and then you
take it, but it's still related to the previous year. I don't
know, you could go either way. Or you could say since you
can't take it the moment it's born, since you can't take it
on ראש חודש אלול *Rosh Chodesh Elul*, then it goes till the
next year. Anyway, רב Rav שמעון *Reb Shimon* says you could actually
take it מעשר Maaser *ma'aser* less than eight days old and sanctify
it less than eight days old. So the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says
like this: ודיליף מבכור ניליף מקדשים *Vede'yalif mibechor ne'yalif mikodashim*, rather than
learning out from בכור bechor *bechor*, which is sanctified when it's מחוסר
זמן mechusar zman, *mechusar zman*, less—not yet its time, so why not
learn out from normal sacrifices that cannot be sanctified? So now we're
going to do the classic thing about to which is it more
comparable. מסתברא מבכור הוה ליה למילף *Mistabra mibechor hava leh lemeylaf*. It
makes more sense to connect מעשר maaser *ma'aser* to בכור bechor. *bechor*,
to learn it out from בכור bechor *bechor*. Why? שכן Shekein, *Sheken*,
here's the way מעשר maaser בהמה *ma'aser behemah* is similar to בכור
Bechor *bechor*: גואל מום mum. תמורה tmura, אכילה *Goel mum tmura achila*.
Okay, redemption, blemish, exchange, eating. There you go, that's clear. So let's
go through them. גואל *Goel* means that neither a בכור bechor, *bechor*
or מעשר maaser *ma'aser* can you redeem, can you be פודה *podeh*,
even with a blemish. A בכור bechor *bechor* with its blemish is
eaten to the כהן kohen. *kohen*, or if there's a question if
the כהן kohen. *kohen* gets it or not, eaten by the ישראל
*Yisrael*, but anyway, classic example, eaten by the כהן Kohen. *kohen*, not
as a קרבן korban, *korban*. And מעשר maaser *ma'aser* with its blemish
is eaten by the ישראל *Yisrael*, but neither of them can be
redeemed. Okay, so their very nature of their קדושה Kedusha *kedusha* is
similar, it cannot be transferred. It's very much about their identity as
first or tenth, and therefore you cannot redeem it and exchange it
and place it on something else. So that's גואל *goel*, means they
can't be redeemed. מום mum, *Mum* is really the similar point, which
is that even with a blemish, they are eaten with a blemish.
They're not like, you know, normally a normal קרבן korban *korban* has
a blemish, you have to redeem it and use the money. You
can't eat a normal קרבן korban. *korban* with a blemish. Here, even
with a blemish, the whole הלכה halachah *halacha* is that you're allowed
to eat it. It's the flip side of not being able to
be redeemed. You can't redeem it, so what do you do if
it has a blemish? You eat it with the blemish. Okay, so
that's the מום *mum*. תמורה *Tmura* means that you can't make a
תמורה *tmura*. If I try to say this animal is an exchange
for the בכור Bechor *bechor*, this animal is an exchange for מעשר
maaser *ma'aser*, תמורה *tmura* is always forbidden. But the question is, is
it effective? So when I do it by a normal קרבן korban.
*korban*, the קדושה Kedusha, *kedusha* applies to the other animal as well.
It expands and applies to the other animal. By בכור bechor. *bechor*
and מעשר *ma'aser*, not. And again, part of the reason is because
בכור bechor *bechor* and מעשר *ma'aser* is very much about their identity
as being a בכור bechor *bechor*, as being the tenth. And it's
not this, you know, abstract קדושה Kedusha *kedusha* that can be instilled
and transferred. These are all linked ideas, right? Because it's about its
identity, you can't remove the קדושה Kedusha *kedusha*, you can't extend it
and transfer it. It's not this abstract thing that's being instilled, it's
about its identity as בכור bechor *bechor* and מעשר *ma'aser*. Alright, so
and finally אכילה *Achila*. What is אכילה *achila*? So רש"י Rashi *Rashi*
says that they're eaten—well, so how's that different than מום *mum*? רש"י
Rashi *Rashi* says it means that they're eaten without being brought as
a קרבן *korban* if they have a מום *mum*. So how's it
different than מום *mum*? Let me just check.
Ah, okay, right, right. רש"י Rashi *Rashi* says, I'm sorry, so רש"י
Rashi *Rashi* says אכילה *achila* means what I said before, that they're
eaten even out not—if they have a מום *mum* they don't have
to be brought as a קרבן *korban*, they can be eaten without
redeeming them. What does מום *mum* mean? מום *Mum* means what we
taught, if you remember last פרק *perek*, that all other קרבנות korbanos.
*korbanot*, if they first have a מום *mum* and then you sanctify
them, the sanctity is never קרבן *korban* sanctity. Right, if my animal,
my sheep, has a מום *mum* and then I try to say
I'm making it an עולה *olah*, that קדושה Kedusha. *kedusha* is never
קדושת קרבן Kedushat Korban, *kedushat korban*. Do you remember this? It's only
קדושה Kedusha. *kedusha* for its value because it never had the ability
to be brought as a קרבן *korban*. The exception to that rule
is חוץ מן הבכור מן המעשר *Chutz min habechor min hama'aser*. For
the same—that בכור bechor *bechor* and מעשר *ma'aser* by definition because it's
the first and because it's the tenth, it gets קדושת קרבן *kedushat
korban* even with the blemish, which doesn't mean I can bring it,
it means I eat it outside of the בית המקדש Beis Hamikdash,
*Beit HaMikdash*, but the nature of the קדושה kedusha *kedusha* is irrespective
of the fact that the blemish preceded it. Okay, so all of
these are very, very linked ideas and have to do with the
fact that the קדושה *kedusha* is not an abstraction that's being instilled,
but it's very much connected to their identity as first and as
tenth. So again, what is it? You can't redeem it, when it
gets a blemish, if you can't redeem it, what do you do
with it? So this is a really
bizarre—never have this before, that something with קדושת קרבן *kedushat korban* and
with a blemish, you eat outside the בית המקדש Beis Hamikdash. *Beit
HaMikdash* without bringing it as a קרבן *korban*. That's a real exception,
and it only applies by בכור ומעשר bechor u-maaser because you can't
redeem. So what do you do? You eat it outside the בית
המקדש, even though it had a blemish that preceded it, its קדושה
is still a full קדושת קרבן, and it doesn't make תמורה, again,
because that's about its identity. So all of these are very much
connected to the idea that it's about its identity and not about
sort of just instilling a קדושה, which then makes sense to apply
it to the idea that it can apply even מחוסר זמן, mechusar
zman. right? Because if it can apply even if the קדושה can
be instilled even when it's a בעל מום, baal mum, maybe the
קדושה can be instilled even if it's מחוסר זמן. mechusar zman. It
is still the tenth, and that maybe automatically gives it the קדושה.
That is רבי שמעון's Rabbi Shimon position.
Yes, very quickly. So when you do your מעשר, you know, like
you take out the בכור bechor already, you can't double count that.
Right. So whatever's left, not בכור. bechor. Right. You put through whether
or not it has a מום. Right, essentially. Yes, so you know
you don't
and it's the tenth one comes out and has a מום, it's
still מעשר and you eat it outside the בית המקדש. That's exactly
the point, correct. So now the גמרא Gemara says like this, אדרבה
מכולהו הוי ליה למילף, Adaraba mikosham hava lei lemilaf, no wait, maybe
מעשר is more similar to normal קרבנות. korbanos Why? שכן, here's the
way it's similar. זכר, Zachar, male, meaning not male, meaning only בכור
bechor has to be male, מעשר and other קרבנות korbanos do not.
קדוש, Kadosh, it is sanctified, which means what? Means that you need
an act to sanctify it. Although we've been emphasizing right, מעשר does
is very fascinating, you know, is interestingly between these two categories. בכור
bechor is by virtue of it being בכור, bechor? you don't have
to do anything. A normal animal, you instill the sanctity. מעשר is
by virtue of it being tenth. But who defined it as tenth?
You did through the act of counting and designating. So it's sort
of midpoint between instilling and natural, you know, sort of natural identity.
So that's what the גמרא Gemara says here. You are the one
that sanctifies or implicitly sanctifies by counting as opposed to בכור bechor,
which you did not. במתנות, B'matanos, both of them you how does
this work in terms of the מתנות? matanos? Oh, the מתנות כהונה,
matanot kehunah, right. מתנות כהונה, Matanot kehunah, I mean they're not, excuse
me. בכור bechor, is a מתנות כהונה, matanot kehunah, goes to a
כהן. מעשר
and and a normal קרבן, let's say a שלמים, shlamim, not a
חטאת, chatas, let's talk about שלמים, shlamim, are eaten by the owners.
Okay, so מעשר and other sort of similar קרבן would be eaten
by the owners and not primarily a gift to the כהן. So
therefore it's similar to that. And פשוט, pashut, it's not a בכור.
bechor, It doesn't have to be a בכור bechor, actually, whereas actually
not only doesn't it have to, it can't, you can't make a
בכור bechor. something else, מעשר or another קרבן. So there are ways
in which it is similar to other קרבן. Now if you ask
me, the first set is more persuasive because the first set has
a lot more to do with its very identity and its very
קדושה. These are more, these are less sort of central aspects. But
the גמרא Gemara thinks you know it's four against four. So the
גמרא Gemara says אלא, ela, you're right. You can't just learn it
by an analogy. רבי שמעון העברה העברה גמירא. Rabbi Shimon ha-avarah ha-avarah
gemiri. Okay, he learns it from a גזירה שוה. gezeira shava. It
says יעבור תחת השבט yaavor tachas hashaves and it says by בכור
bechor? והעברתם כל פטר רחם. veha-avartem kol peter rechem. So the גזירה
שוה gezeira shava links it even though you can't do it straight
by just comparison because you could have made the comparison either way.
Okay, but either way I think that that's quite interesting thinking about
the comparisons between בכור bechor. ומעשר about these two types of of
קרבנות korbanos which a lot have to do with their identity rather
than instilling קדושה and some of the implications of that.
And you take out all female?
No, מעשר we said זכר. zachar. No, only that's the way מעשר
is like other קרבנות because only the בכור bechor, is זכר. zachar.
And only the בכור bechor is the בכור. bechor. זכר Zachar means
not זכר. zachar. Okay? They both share the fact that they are
different, as you know, sometimes it says the not in the category.
Okay, like, okay, I'm sorry.
Don't have to be זכר.
zachar. Yeah, doesn't have to, not only doesn't have to, right, doesn't
have to, right, okay, opposite day. All right anyway, so the גמרא
Gemara says like this. All right now finally, okay, we're done with
that. That was I think quite interesting. The issue about the comparison
of בכור bechor, to מעשר and the specific application of מחוסר זמן.
We've dealt with the whole very complicated scenario of, you know, whether
it what do you call it about about when exactly did it
give birth, once or twice, did it wait a month or not,
you count five full months, not five full months. Fine, whatever that
was. Now we move on to back to I think you know
one of the central points of the משנה Mishna which is you
know which is the animal gives birth, you assume it's a בכור
bechor if it's within a certain age, but then the counter argument
which was, wait, it might have miscarried before. And now it's the
question about how do you know, let's not take a case like
we're dealing before, you bought an animal and you don't know its
history. You actually own this animal, something comes out of it, how
do you know if it's a miscarriage or not and will this
thing exempt you from בכור? bechor, Now there's two questions. One is
just the question of is this actually an aborted pregnancy? And the
other question is for it to be a miscarriage that exempts from
בכור, bechor. the animal has to have been considered to some degree
developed. For humans that means after 40 days. Okay, so if there's
a miscarriage after 40 days, the next child is not a בכור,
bechor, less than 40 days it is. Okay, so if... We have
to determine in the animal scenario, since we're talking about miscarriages as
exempting, how do you know it's a miscarriage that will exempt? A,
that it's a miscarriage, and B, that it will exempt. So let's
take a look. So the גמרא Gemara says like this: היכי דמי
טינוף? Heichi dami tinof? What is the case of miscarriage? How do
you sort of know? How do you assess it? So אמר רבא,
Amar Rava, כדאמרי רעותא דצלצא, kedamri re'usa deTzaltza, like the shepherds of
צלצא Tzaltza say, name of a place, עצר חיותא. atzar chayuta. It's
sort of like, רש"י Rashi. says this means essentially
the womb, you know, was sort of was closed up and somehow,
you know, somehow somehow like squeezed the animal, or it's more described,
not describing what you're seeing, but describing the scenario that the, because
of the, that it either means like its life was squeezed out,
but רש"י Rashi says it means that the womb was somehow closed
or not, and therefore it came out in this aborted way. Of
course, the womb is supposed to be closed until it's ready to
be born. Anyway, that's what, that's how רש"י explains that.
נעצר רחמה, Ne'etzar rachmah, its womb was closed, ונימוק העובר, venimok ha'ubar,
and the fetus dissolved. So I'm exactly not sure exactly how that
gets from the עצר חיותא atzar chayuta and the relationship to being
the womb being closed. But חיותא chayuta could also just mean the
life, the life of it was sort of somehow held back or
squeezed out. ושמואל אמר, U'Shmuel amar, anyway, not clear because it seems
like we're trying to explain the, how what it looks like, which
is more שמואל's Shmuel response. ושמואל אמר, U'Shmuel amar, בבואי דדמא. bavu'ei
dedama. It's like, it's like sort of bubbles of blood, like there's
sort of like, you know, a sort of congealed thing, right, some
type, some type of thing that's a very bloody discharge. Okay, so
now the גמרא Gemara says neither that is too helpful. How am
I supposed to make an assessment based on that? So the גמרא
Gemara says וצריך להראות לחכם. vetzarich leharot lechacham. You've got to show
it to somebody who knows. You've got to show it to a
חכם chacham who will assess whether it is really a miscarriage or
not. So the גמרא Gemara says, you'll enjoy this, חכם מנא ידע?
chacham mena yada? So how does a guy who's in the בית
מדרש, Beit Midrash, what does he know about animal miscarriages? So the
גמרא Gemara says, אמר רב פפא, Amar Rav Papa, רועה חכם. ro'eh
chacham. We mean a shepherd who is a, who is a scholar,
a shepherd who's an expert, who knows what a miscarriage looks like.
Show it to an expert. Okay, so after that whole גמרא Gemara,
about animals giving birth, Bobby, you're very relieved, right? So the גמרא
Gemara says in the end, you want to know what a miscarriage
is, you ask an expert shepherd, you don't ask a rabbi.
So I wonder if a woman can get pregnant, is that not
child
abuse?
Okay, moving on. All right, now אמר רב חסדא, Amar Rav Chisda,
הרי אמרו, harei amru, behold they said, יצירת הולד באשה ארבעים יום.
yetzirat havlad be'ishah arba'im yom. So we say that the fetus forms
in a human woman in forty days. And the relevance to that,
I mean, first of all, there's interesting questions about the relevance to
that to positions about abortion, but in the גמרא, Gemara the immediate
relevance is that if a woman miscarries less than forty days, she's
not טמאה לידה, teme'ah leidah, and she's not טמאה, teme'ah, the woman
who gives birth automatically it makes her טמאה, teme'ah, but it's not
if it's less than forty days, a miscarriage less than forty days.
And the other issue here is בכור, bechor that afterwards, if it's
a miscarriage after forty days, then the afterwards the child, the live
child will not be a בכור, bechor, and if it's less than
that, it will be.
So what does יצירת הולד yetzirat havlad mean?
What no,
the words mean that this is when the fetus has formed. Now,
formed to what degree is the question. So at different stages, so
first of all, they do say, people like pointing out that they
say that, you know, brain waves are first detected after about six
weeks, which is roughly forty days. I don't know if that's what
the גמרא Gemara had in mind, but people like making that comparison.
The גמרא Gemara speaks more about somehow the limbs starting to take
on some type of a shape, like it takes on some type
of a human, if you're talking in the human scenario, some type
of a human shape after, is that true? Do people know the
different stages of fetal development?
It's easy to look up, funny. Yeah, go ahead, look up fetal
development.
I'm serious, you know, to what degree, I remember this was a
long time ago when I took biology, a picture of like all
these different embryos in an early stage of development, and they're like,
which one is the human? I picked the horse. I mean, I
couldn't tell the difference. You really cannot tell at forty days. So
go ahead, look it
up on Wikipedia now, fetal development. But the point is at some
stage it starts having human form, its limbs are somewhat formed, that
was decided to be forty days. That gave it its identity as
an actual, like, again, it doesn't mean, you know, it doesn't mean
it's a full human, that's the question of abortion, but at least
it's a question of that identifies it as a fetus and the
birth as a, you know, as a miscarriage.
So, and for these הלכות, halachot, it's a לידה leidah and it
has the relevance for בכור. bechor, So the גמרא Gemara says, בעי
רב חסדא, ba'ei Rav Chisda, רב חסדא Rav Chisda asked, בבהמה בכמה?
bevehemah bekammah? How much about animals? How long does the fetus have
to develop before it's then considered to be an actual, you know,
halachic miscarriage to the point where afterwards it will not be a
בכור? bechor? So אמר ליה רב פפא לאביי, Amar leh Rav Papa
le'Abaye, רב פפא Rav Papa said to אביי, Abaye, לאו היינו דזעירי,
lav hainu deZe'iri, isn't that what זעירי Ze'iri meant? דאמר. de'amar. זעירי
Zeiri said אין נפלים פחות משלושים יום, ein nefalim pachot mishloshim yom,
there's no miscarriage less than thirty days. And I got to tell
you, that is what it sounds like זעירי Zeiri meant. It's not
how we've been interpreting it for the last two days, but that's
what it sounds like he means, less than thirty days development is
not considered miscarriage. So the גמרא Gemara says no, ההוא לקבל איתמר.
hahu lekabla itmar. The way we've been understanding זעירי Zeiri as we
have for the last two days means after miscarriage, the animal won't
get pregnant again for another thirty days. That's how we've been interpreting,
but actually, what the גמרא Gemara just has suggested here, what רב
פפא Rav Pappa said, sounded a lot more like the words: there
is no miscarriage less than thirty days. It's not there's no pregnancy
after miscarriage less than thirty days. It sounds like it's not considered
a miscarriage with less than thirty days development, but the גמרא Gemara
is not reading it that way and the גמרא Gemara leaves it
unresolved. Unresolved. How do we know how much it has to be
in terms of, in terms of to be considered a real sort
of that the fetus had already developed? Again, that would I guess
be something you would ask an expert shepherd. Okay, so now the
גמרא Gemara says, now that we're done about buying from a non-Jew,
we switch to buying from a Jew, and then we get to
the question that Mike raised before about, you know, until now we've
been talking about what assumptions can you make. How about can you
actually trust people based on the claims that they're making? So let's
take a look. Before we go, Mordechai, have you any answer for
us,
fetal development, limbs find form? It first materializes as head and eyes
and only later begins the...
Right, how about the torso and those limbs? When do those start
being formed?
Looks like week eight is when the limbs take a recognizable...
Aha, so that's after day forty. That's fifty-six. Okay. All right, so
now the גמרא Gemara says like this. Okay, איתמר, itmar, מצינו הוא
לוקח מעובד כוכבים. matzinu hu lokeach meoved kochavim. So we taught a
ברייתא, Baraita, we've seen the case about buying from a non-Jew, where
you just have to try to make assumptions whether the animal has
had a firstborn or not. לוקח מישראל מאי, lokeach miYisrael mai, what
if you buy from a Jew?
So אמר רב, amar Rav, בכור ודאי. bechor vadai. If you buy
from a Jew and he said nothing, you can definitely assume that
this animal has not yet had its firstborn and the firstborn is
a בכור. bechor And he's even given to the כהן. Why? How
can you make that assumption, he didn't say anything?
דאי איתא דבכרה אשתבוחי הוה משתבח ליה. de'im itta debackera ishtabochei hava
mishtabach lei. He would have praised it. Praised it why? He would
have used it as a selling point. Why do you think it
would be a selling point that the animal had already given birth?
You don't have to worry!
You don't have to worry about giving בכור, bechor this animal's already
given birth. Okay, it's pre-used, like it's no longer used cars, it's
pre-owned cars. So a
pre-בכורed bechor. animal. So that's what רש"י says, although תוספות Tosafot has
a different גרסא girsa of רש"י. תוספות Tosafot says that at the
end. תוספות's Tosafot גרסא, girsa, but anyway, תוספות Tosafot says that the
animal, once it has survived pregnancy and childbirth once, it's healthier, like
you know that it's able to have anything then... Well, okay, we'll
get to non-Jew in a minute. You'll know that it is able
to have children without it, without risking its life, because it actually
has gone through that process once. Anyway, so the other thing though
רש"י just says is what I think would have occurred to us
more obviously, is that you don't have to worry about בכור. bechor,
So because he didn't say anything, we can infer that that's not
the case and therefore that you can even go to the point
of saying it is ודאי, vadai, the first animal that it gives
birth to is a בכור, bechor? you can assume ודאי vadai it
has not given birth yet.
Wasn't there a point where בכור bechor here is on a פטר
רחם peter rechem and not to bring in the rest of the
בכורים? bechorim? So yeah, yeah, yeah, yeah. Okay.
Did they also say that subsequent
children are stronger? Did it say that?
It said that the single birth was stronger than the double birth.
Did it say... Oh wait, you might be right, wait, hold on,
I'm going
to lose my
audio...
Wait, wait, you might be right, hold on, the memory games...
I've got to go and find to remember where that was... All
right, anyway... Somewhere in the second paragraph. All right, hold on,
just give me a second...
Okay...
Yeah, דהא לא ביכרה שביח טפי... deha lo bikra shevi'ach tvei...
No, there it said the other one, there it said the one
born to the animal that had not yet given birth, the firstborn,
would have been,
you know, a better animal. So actually you're saying... what? Okay, so
that doesn't fit the אשתבוחי הוה משתבח. ishtabochei hava mishtabach. But it
was a very nice application. Okay, so the first statement is that
through silence you can assume that it definitely has not given birth.
That's the first answer, that's what רב says.
ושמואל אמר, u'Shmuel amar, שמואל אמר, Shmuel amar, בכור ספק. bechor safek.
No, you can't prove anything from silence. Why? לשחיטה קבעי לה. lishchita
ka ba'ei lei. Why is he not saying praised it, oh this
animal has already given birth, no problems? Because maybe he figures you're
going to slaughter it and it's not even worth mentioning. Okay, so
you can't really infer anything from silence.
But why not also talk about the other things? So what Mordechai
says might be that he said that if you're interested in shechting
it, the fact that it's already given birth is actually a downside
because it means the meat becomes tougher after a certain point. Okay.
So anyway, so Shmuel says you cannot infer anything from silence. רבי
יוחנן אמר Rabbi Yochanan amar and רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan says the
exact opposite. חולין ודאי, chullin vadai, it's definitely חולין. chullin. It definitely
has already given birth. Why? מאי טעמא, mai ta'ama, what's the reason?
אם איתא דלא בכרה, im issa d'lo bichra, if it has not
already given birth, כיון דאיכא איסורא, kivan d'ika issura, since when if
I'm selling it to Mordechai and it hasn't given birth and I
know that Mordechai, what, you know, might take the first animal and
not realize it's a בכור, bechor, so I obviously am going to
be a responsible person and tell Mordechai to make sure that he
doesn't accidentally misuse a בכור. bechor, So אודועי הוי מודע ליה, udoi
havai modi leh, I would have told Mordechai about that. So it's
very interesting, right? Are my interests as the seller, are we assuming
that my focus is in terms of making a good profit? Sure.
And then I would be praising it, and from my silence we
assume that it has not given birth, or do we say the
opposite? That when I'm selling something I'm very concerned about not making
people sin, and therefore if it was, if there was a problem,
if there was an issue he had to be careful about it
being a בכור, bechor, I would have said something to him. So
the whole spectrum of possibilities. תני כוותיה דרבי יוחנן דאמר חולין, tani
kivatei d'Rabbi Yochanan d'amar chullin, we taught like רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan
that says it's חולין, chullin, that you can assume from silence that
there are no halachic problems. How do you know that? Because we
taught the following. אם לא הודיעו, im lo hodiao, remember we said
that there are times, four times during the year, that the butcher
has to tell people that I sold the mother or the child
today, because since everybody is eating meat at those four times of
the year, you assume the person is going to go shecht it.
And if you sold the mother that day or the child that
day, then the next person who shechts it will have shechted אותו
ואת בנו. oso v'es bno. Okay. What if the שוחט shochet didn't
tell you anything? You know, he didn't say 'I sold the mother
today,' he didn't say 'I didn't sell the mother today.' What can
you assume? So it says הולך ושוחט ואינו נמנע. holech v'shochet v'eino
nimna. You can assume it's not a problem. So you see that
from the silence of the seller we assume there's no halachic problem.
If there were a halachic issue he would have said it. So
here too from the silence of the seller we can assume there's
no halachic problem. But the גמרא Gemara says, לימא תיהוי תיובתא דרב
ושמואל? leima teivei tivta d'Rav u'Shmuel? Maybe this really supports רבי יוחנן
Rabbi Yochanan and rejects the other two approaches that says that maybe
he's silent but maybe there still is a problem? So the גמרא
Gemara says, no, there's a difference between the cases. התם במוכר תליא
מילתא הכא בלוקח תליא מילתא. hasam b'mocher talyo miltasa hacha b'lokeach talyo
miltasa. There it's about the seller, here it's about the buyer. Now
what does that mean, there it's about the seller, here it's about
the buyer? So רש״י Rashi says the following. רש״י Rashi says we
learned out, if you remember way back in חולין, Chullin, we learned
out how do you know that the seller is supposed to tell
you that he sold the mother today? We learned it out from
a פסוק pasuk that, let me just see רש״י Rashi quotes the
פסוק, pasuk, יום אחד. yom echad. יום המיוחד, yom hamiyuchad, it's certain
particular days that you have to announce it. So the way רש״י
Rashi reads it is there's a specific mandate even learned out from
a verse that the sellers have to tell you. So if they're
not telling you, you can infer from their silence it's not the
case. When there isn't a mandate, then it is the buyer's responsibility
to ask, not the seller's responsibility to tell you. So since there's
no mandate for me to tell you that it's a בכור bechor,
or not a בכור, it's your responsibility, you can't infer anything from
my silence. So רש״י Rashi makes it based on a verse. תוספות,
Tosafos, interestingly, makes it based more on facts than on a verse.
And תוספות Tosafos says, you know, what is the likelihood that in
a time where, let me just double check תוספות Tosafos again to
remind myself, hold on,
yeah look at the תוספות, Tosafos, התם במוכר תליא מילתא, hasam b'mocher
talyo miltasa, תוספות Tosafos says like this, דיודע מוכר בלוקח שקנה לשחוט.
d'yodea mocher b'lokeach shekani lishchot. If I know you're planning on shechting
and then I'm not going to tell you, then I am causing
you to sin. I know you're planning on shechting, I know I
sold the mother today, I know the mother's going to be shechted,
clearly I have knowledge that what you're about to do will lead
to a sin. Clearly that's my responsibility, not because there's some verse
like רש״י Rashi says, just the facts on the ground. I know
that I've sold the mother, I know the mother's going to be
shechted today, I know what you're planning on doing, so I better
tell you because I'm the only one that's going to be able
to prevent you from sinning. How is that different here? So הכא
בלוקח תליא מילתא, hacha b'lokeach talyo miltasa, look at the next תוספות,
Tosafos, שעליו לחקור במן ציון אם חייבת בבכורה. she'alav lachkor b'man tziyun
im chayaves bivchora. Because in that case, selling you an animal, it's
not like you're about to sin with it, maybe you'll play it
safe, maybe you'll shecht, who knows what you're going to do. So
there it becomes your responsibility to ask, not my responsibility to tell.
So according to תוספות... Tosafos...
you have as information... what?
I have the information, but do I have a responsibility? So according
to תוספות, Tosafos, I like תוספות Tosafos better than רש״י Rashi because
רש״י Rashi makes it sort of arbitrary based on a verse. תוספות
Tosafos says like in this exchange, how much is it my responsibility,
how much is it buyer beware? I mean, we're not talking about
like misleading in terms of the sale, we're talking about protecting people
halachically, but how much is it My responsibility, how much is that
your responsibility? Okay, so תוספות Tosafos *Tosfos* says that and oh, the
other point I skipped in the previous תוספות *Tosfos* was when you're
buying a meat from me, you have no reason to assume that
I דוקא *davka* sold its mother or I דוקא *davka* sold the
child today. So you have no particular reason to ask. I know
all the facts, I know that if I don't say anything you're
going to sin. So I have the knowledge and I and I
know what the story is. You have no par- there's nothing that
should make you want to ask that question because why do we
assume that the same person who sold the mother sold the child,
you know? So therefore that's fully my responsibility fully is on my
shoulders. The reverse is the case by the בכור *bechor*. In that
case, it's quite possible you're not going to sin, right? It's quite
possible you're going to שחט *shecht* it, quite possible first of all
the thing might be a girl, might have, you know, who knows
what, right? So therefore that's not particularly my responsibility. I don't know
where that's going. Maybe you'll just play it safe and wait till
it gets a מום *mum*. There's nothing that particularly heightens my responsibility
there. On the other hand, it's a very simple question, right? It's
not like I have no reason to suspect you sold the mother
or sold the child. It's very reasonable that this animal might not
have given birth yet. So therefore you do have a reason to
want to suspect it might be a problem. It's not particularly my
responsibility and therefore it's and therefore my being silent you can't-
But even if I buy- even if I buy an animal because
you know we said that after a year it's definitely given birth.
Right.
So- Right, that's an interesting question because the גמרא Gemara, *Gemara* seems
to be saying when you buy from ישראל *Yisrael*, let's ignore how
old it is and infer something from the silence. So it seems
to be right irrespective of how old it is. So you could
have thought- so what you're saying back makes a lot of sense
that maybe you could say that, you know, at a certain age
you have no reason to be asking because you could have- right,
I hear that.
Anyway, there isn't just to bring out the biology of it all
that you can examine an animal and- Oh really? I mean I
don't know about all animals, I know about like cows, there's a
physical difference between the cow who hasn't given birth yet and the
cow who has given birth. Really? Very interesting. And it's obvious? It's
internal? External? External. Yeah, because the udder shifts.
Well, the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* did talk about whether it's lactating. Right.
So the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* had talked which is essentially that point.
Right. So the udder shifts and changes. Right. It's even before you
look for scarring and tears or anything like that.
Wow. Very interesting. Very interesting. Okay, so anyway, so you're saying that
what?
They say in the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* is ignoring that?
Yeah, basically according to the positions of body one or body the
other way, it'll be irrespective of the age. So we have the
following, I just want to wrap this up by saying, so we
have the following: You buy from ישראל *Yisrael*, what can you assume
in terms of the silence? So one opinion is you can assume
in terms of the silence that it definitely has not or else
it would have been, excuse me, praised that it had. The other
says you can infer from the silence it definitely has because because
what do you call it because otherwise it would be the seller's
responsibility to tell you, which is an interesting question about seller's responsibility
and his sense of being caring about your sort of religious observance.
And then the middle position it's a ספק *safek*. Now the question
is all of that is when the person says nothing. The implication
is the implication
is
before we get to a non-Jew, let's say the seller actually tells
you, let's say the seller actually tells you explicitly, okay, what whether
it has. Clearly it seems that if he tells you explicitly you
trust him because the whole point is what can we infer from
the implicit. But it seems like explicit you can trust him. And
then the question is what if the non-Jew tells you explicitly what
is the story there? Thank you. So let's look at תוספות *Tosfos*
about this, okay, where תוספות *Tosfos* says אשתבוחי משתבח ליה *ishtabuchei mishtabach
lei*. תוספות
*Tosfos* says פירש בקונטרס *peirash bekuntres*, no that's just not that one.
One minute, where did he talk about? ויש לומר *v'yesh lomar*, yes
it is that one, end of the first wide line. ויש לומר
מפירושו *v'yesh lomar mipeirusho*, you can infer from רש״י *Rashi*, oh
let's start from the beginning then. פירש בקונטרס *peirash bekuntres* שכבר ביכרה
ולא תסתכן בלידה *shekvar bikra v'lo tistakein b'leida*, he would praise it
because he'd say it had given birth and it won't be, you
know, endangered if it gives birth again. אבל *aval*, this is his
version of רש״י *Rashi*, this is not in our רש״י *Rashi*. אבל
עובד כוכבים *aval oveid kochavim*, a non-Jew, אינמי אמר ליה הכי *inami
amar lei hachi*, even if he told you this animal has already
given birth, אין בדבריו אמת *ein bidvarav emes*, you can't assume he's
telling the truth. Maybe he's saying it just in order to make
his wares look better and therefore you can't trust him. And in
this case and then you discount it. ויש לומר מפירושו *v'yesh lomar
mipeirusho*, you can learn from רש״י *Rashi*, דעובד כוכבים אפילו מסיח לפי
תומו *d'oveid kochavim afilu masiach lefi tumo*, even if he's not doing
it in order to make a profit, just talking sort of like,
you know, in passing or not talking in order to tell you
a halachic point really. אינו נאמן *eino ne'eman*, you can't trust him.
Right, I'm sorry. מסיח לפי תומו *masiach lefi tumo* means he's not
telling it to you to answer a halachic question that it's clear
you're asking him about for halachic concerns. He just happened to be
saying, hey this animal has already given birth, you can't trust him.
דלהשביח מקח דעובד כוכבים אומר כן *d'lehashbiach mekach d'oveid kochavim omer kein*,
he's saying it in order to, you know, to make his wares
look more expensive and therefore you can't assume that he's telling the
truth. But then he says... And then he goes on. Okay, so
this becomes an interesting question which is a general halachic question about
trusting, you know, about sort of testimony of Jews, testimony of non-Jews,
using them within halachic context. Okay, and there's a couple of concerns
that come up within the issue about the non-Jewish testimony. One is
in certain areas, there's a question which is if somebody is not
part of the halachic system, how much do they care enough about
the details, meaning not that they're intentionally lying, but like they're like,
you know, irrelevant to them, like, you know, like sometimes very often
somebody says, you know, somebody says yeah, I went to my doctor,
you know, and and they told me not to fast on יום
כיפור. You know, if you don't understand what the weight of the
issue is—I'm not saying sometimes that's not the right suggestion, I'm just
saying that sometimes if you don't understand what the weight of the
issue is—what is this נארישקייט narishkeit fasting? Of course you shouldn't fast,
you know? So, so that's one issue. More often the question does
become about question about trust and and you know there the גמרא
Gemara sort of looks at a constellation of factors. On the one
hand, to what degree might somebody be misrepresenting in terms of in
order to make a bigger profit? And on the other hand, what
are the consequences of misrepresenting? Will it endanger their, you know, their
reputation and so on? So those are the types of concerns that
the גמרא Gemara. raises. Now, lest you, you know, go ahead and—now
of course the גמרא, Gemara I think if the גמרא Gemara just
raised those issues in general, we wouldn't be troubled. I think we're
a little bit more troubled that the גמרא Gemara particularly raises them
by non-Jews and not by Jews. Assumes that by Jews, you know,
that at least by Jews—and again this gets back to the question
about Jews vis-a-vis Jews, Jews vis-a-vis non-Jews. Is it making general statements
that non-Jews, you know, aren't as trustworthy or is it speaking about
the specific relationships between Jews and non-Jews that when it comes to
them, you know, vis-a-vis Jews, there's there was a lot of animosity
and so on. But anyway, these are these are some of the
issues.
What? It could also be about just protection of the system like
לפני עור Lifnei Iver and ערבות Areivus and things like that that
exist within...
Right, that how much are Jews—like we just said before—because Jews are
concerned about making other Jews sin, they're going to be extra honest
about, you know, again, we're not talking about just self-interest. Right. Well,
yeah, they don't want to because they don't want to be sinning
by making somebody else sin. Right, you know, so that gets to
the other point, that if you have the halachic system and you
understand all the weights and the consequences, that's going to make you
more honest when dealing with those particular issues. רב מרדכי Rav Mordechai
says it nicely. I mean, I don't care about lying to you
and about you sinning, but I do care about me sinning by
making you sin.
But even over here, I mean, you know, we have three different
opinions about whether it's חולין Chullin to...
I understand, I understand. Anyway, I just wanted to point out that
the תוספות does raise this question about that. Let's just, and you
understand
that you have to know, so then asking a non-Jew wouldn't help,
essentially, right? I mean, wasn't that what Tosafos was already launching? That's
a good point.
Yeah. Okay, so let's now move on to the next משנה. Mishnah.
רבי אליעזר בן יעקב אומר Rabbi Eliezer ben Yaakov omer בהמה גסה
ששפכה חררת דם behemah gassah she'shafachah hararat dam הרי זו תקבר harei
zo tikkaver פפורה מן
הבכורה. peturah min habechorah. So let's say you had a large non-grazing
animal like a cow, that it basically, you know, came out of
its body came sort of lumps, clumps of blood. Okay, so now
the question is: is this what? Clots? Yeah. Do you call a
clot something standalone? I thought a clot was the way that it
stopped up something else is a clot.
No, the blood that congeals is a clot.
Oh, I thought it's only clotting if it's stopping the flow of
something. No? Okay, anyway, clumps or clots of blood. Anyway, so the
question is: is this a miscarriage or not? So it says הרי
זו תקבר, harei zo tikkaver, you bury it, because presumably not that
animals need burial, but
because—well, we'll see in the גמרא why—one reason is if it's a
נבילה neveilah you don't want other people to become טמא. tamei. Also,
if it's a בכור, what's the הלכה about a בכור? That now,
you know, you can't eat it, it's a בכור that's a נבילה
neveilah and it has קדושת בכור. kedushas bechor. If it's the first—if
it's the firstborn and it's a miscarriage, it's not just a normal
נבילה. neveilah. It's something that has קדושת בכור, kedushas bechor, so you
can't even get benefit from it. So you can't benefit from it,
you bury it.
This also indicates why...
Oh, because of that miscarriage.
It might have miscarried earlier than the biological changes.
Right. That's a good point. That's a good point. The גמרא mentioned
the miscarriage before. Anyway, and it's exempt from בכור because the next
birth—the next birth is exempt because you consider this to be a
בכור. Okay, so here you see that you basically assume that this
is a miscarriage fetus, it is a בכור, it is buried, and
the next animal is exempt.
Let's see the גמרא. תני רבי חייא Tani Rabbi Hiyya אינה מטמאה
לא במגע ולא במשא. einah metammah lo bemaga velo bemassa.
So רבי חייא Rabbi Hiyya says it does not cause טומאה, tumah,
not touching or carrying, meaning it's not a נבילה. neveilah. So if
it's not a נבילה, neveilah, means that the animal wasn't formed, so
why are you burying it and why is the next animal exempt
from בכור? So the גמרא says: ומאחר דאינה מטמאה לא במגע ולא
במשא, ume'achar de'einah metammah lo bemaga velo bemassa, if it doesn't cause
טומאה, tumah, אמאי תקבר, amai tikkaver, why do you bury it? כדי
לפרסם שנפטרה מן הבכורה. kedei lefarsem she'niptarah min habechorah. Not because this
animal is a נבילה, neveilah, but because to tell you that the
mother is exempt from בכור and it's done by... By burying it
it says, "Ah, we're treating this as a birth," and therefore know
that the second birth is exempt. Of course, that's to beg the
question: למימרא דולד מעליא היא? le-memra de-valad malya hi? So you're saying
then that it really is a fetus, because otherwise it wouldn't exempt
the mother. So we're back to our first question: ואמאי אינו מטמא
לא במגע ולא במשא? ve-amai eino metame lo be-maga velo be-massa? Back
to our first question. So why doesn't it cause טומאה? tumah? If
it's a real fetus and exempts the mother for בכור, why doesn't
it cause טומאה? tumah? So אמר רבי יוחנן amar Rabbi Yochanan משום
ביטול ברוב נגעו בה. mishum bittul be-rov nague bah. It's because it
is nullified in the majority. What does that mean? Yes, there is
some fetus mixed up here, but there's also a lot of non-fetus
here, a lot of blood, a lot, you know, from the womb
and a lot of other things, and therefore it won't cause טומאה.
tumah. There is a fetus here, and the mother is exempt from
בכור, but it won't cause טומאה tumah because it is not, like,
you know, obviously present. So the גמרא says ואזדא רבי יוחנן לטעמיה,
ve-azda Rabbi Yochanan le-taameih, he goes according to his reasoning, דאמר רבי
יוחנן de-amar Rabbi Yochanan רבי אלעזר רבי יעקב רבי שמעון אמרו דבר
אחד. Rabbi Elazar Rabbi Yaakov Rabbi Shimon amru davar echad. רבי אלעזר
בן יעקב Rabbi Elazar ben Yaakov and רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon said
the same thing. רבי אלעזר בן יעקב Rabbi Elazar ben Yaakov הא
דאמרן, ha de-amran, רבי אלעזר בן יעקב Rabbi Elazar ben Yaakov we
said that although there's a fetus here and the mother is exempt
from בכור, nevertheless there's no טומאה tumah because it's mixed up with
everything else and it loses its identity. ורבי שמעון מאי היא, ve-Rabbi
Shimon mai hi, what's ורבי שמעון? ve-Rabbi Shimon? דתניא de-tanya we
taught... דתנן de-tenan we taught in
the
משנה: Mishnah: השליא בבית הבית טמא. ha-shilya ba-bayit ha-bayit tame. לא שהשליא
ולד, lo she-ha-shilya valad, not that the placenta itself is the fetus,
אלא שאין שליא בלא ולד. ela she-ein shilya belo valad. There would
not be a placenta without a fetus. So if there's a placenta
in the house, then there somehow is a dissolved fetus within it
and the house is טמא tame because of a dead body. רבי
שמעון אומר, Rabbi Shimon omer, רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon says: ולד נימוק
עד שלא יצא, valad nimok ad she-lo yatza, that the infant has
dissolved before coming out and therefore it does not cause טומאה. tumah.
Now, what does that mean it dissolved? But still it's somewhere. So
the גמרא explains, not here but implicitly here, that because it's dissolved
and it's mixed in with the placenta and with a lot of
other liquids and so on, since it's not enough obviously present, it
does not cause טומאה. tumah. So here you have an interesting scenario
according to רבי חייא, Rabbi Chiyya, which is: the mother gave birth
to a fetus, which is enough to make the mother exempt from
בכור, but the fetus loses its identity, right? Because it gets mixed
up with this other stuff. So therefore the fetus itself does not
cause טומאה tumah because it's mixed up with this other stuff. You
can't derive benefit because there's still a fetus there and you have
to bury it, and you bury it to announce that the mother
is exempt, but the mother gave birth to a fetus without the
fetus retaining its identity. All right, to be continued.
צד הרחם tzad ha-rechem just means very literal.